Guide to the Hands Off Washington Whatcom County Coalition Council records 1988-1996; 1994-1995
Western Washington University, Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
Hands Off Washington, Whatcom County Coalition Council records
1988-1996
1994-1995
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies Goltz-Murray Building 808 25th St Bellingham, WA 98225-9123 Phone: 360 650 7534 Email: cpnws@wwu.edu
XOE_CPNWS0139handsoff
Hands Off Washington (Organization). Whatcom County Coalition Council
4 linear feet
The organization Hands Off Washington (HOW) was created to defeat Washington State initiatives 608 and 610 which threatened the civil rights of state and local public employees based on their actual or perceived sexual orientation. The Whatcom County HOW Coalition Council records date from 1989 to 1996 and consists of the organization's financial records, press releases, fundraising events, emails, office logs, pamphlets, newsletters and other printed materials, state level strategies, other like minded groups, subject files relating to gay and lesbian issues, video and audio tapes, opposition files and newspaper clippings, letters to the editor (for and against) the initiatives and gay and lesbian rights, as well as workshop and speaker information.
Hands Off Washington (HOW) was a project of the Washington Citizens for Fairness (WCF) which lasted from 1993 to 1997. WCF, a state-wide organization, was a coalition of concerned citizens and organizations with the specific aim of preserving the civil rights of all Washington citizens. HOW was created to specifically oppose initiatives 608 and 610, which sought to limit the rights of Washington citizens and legalize discrimination based on sexual orientation. Quoting from the official ballot summaries:
Initiative 608, sponsored by the Equal Rights, Not Special Rights Committee. “This measure would prohibit the state of Washington and its political subdivisions from enacting or enforcing any law or policy that grants protection against discrimination or that recognizes or provides any benefit, right, standing, or privilege to homosexuals or other persons on the basis of sexual orientation. This measure also would bar common schools, their employees, volunteers, and guests from discussing or presenting homosexuality, bisexuality, transexuality, or transvestism as appropriate, positive, or healthy in any respect.”-Initiate 608 Summary, 1994-03-29
Initiative 610, was sponsored by the Citizens Alliance of Washington. “This measure would prohibit governments from according rights, status or protection from discrimination based on homosexuality; from expending funds through governmental or educational institutions to promote, approve, or present homosexuality as a positive, healthy, or acceptable condition; from recognizing same-sex marriages and gender change alterations; and from awarding homosexuals custody of their own or other children in adoption or other child custody proceedings. The measure would grant enforcement standing to residents and non-profit entities.” -Initiative 610 Summary, 1994-03-29
Hands Off Washington Whatcom County Coalition Council was a county branch of the state-wide HOW project. Originally, this branch encompassed only Whatcom County, but in 1995, it incorporated both Whatcom and Skagit Counties. This branch contributed to the statewide effort to oppose discriminatory initiatives and prevent them from getting on the ballot. Through community involvement, strategic planning, fundraisers, and a public education campaign, the initiatives never received the necessary signatures to appear on the ballot. Initiatives 608 and 610 reappeared a year later as initiatives 166 and 167 only to fail for a second time, like their predecessors. In 1995, HOW mobilized a campaign to put their own gay rights initiative on the ballot. However, it was shot down by legislators who claimed it was unconstitutional for citizens to vote on the civil rights of a minority. This right, opponents claimed, should be reserved for legislators. Two years later, HOW proposed another initiative, 677, which would have banned employment discrimination based on sexual orientation. This initiative, however, was voted on by Washington citizens and defeated. Unlike earlier defensive measures, this proactive approach received mixed support from the gay and lesbian community throughout the state. After this defeat, HOW ceased to be and changed their name to Equality Washington.
These records contain documents relating to the Hands Off Washington (HOW) campaign in Whatcom County. These records span from 1988 to 1996. However, the bulk of the material ranges from 1994 to 1995. Contained in these records are administrative and financial records as well as a large amount of subject and reference material relating to gay and lesbian issues, but not specifically limited to either Whatcom County or Washington State. The campaigns against anti-gay rights initiatives such as 608 and 610 as well as 167 and 166 are very well documented in these records. They, however, contain less information concerning later issues such as HOW's gay rights initiative and the organization's dissolution.
The administrative records document both the coordination of meetings and committees of this organization and the financial, such as donations and expenditures. The meeting minutes include both steering committee agendas as well as executive council minutes. They deal with topics such as newsletter information, youth, campus and rural outreach, fundraising, local media monitoring, volunteer coordination, retreats, and events. These records also contain forms that HOW used for potential financial donors, members and general information gathering.
The newsletters, while not a complete run, nevertheless document the official position and news of this HOW branch. They span from July of 1994 to June 1996. Missing issues include July and November of 1995 and April of 1996. Also included in this series are a few other newsletters from other HOW county coalitions.
Speaker and workshop files record the training of both organizational members and educational speakers. Speaker training packets constitute the majority of this series; they contain question and answer sections, samples speeches, newspaper articles, speaking techniques and advice, and other resources pertinent for the training of HOW educational speakers. These files illustrate one method by which HOW ensured that discriminatory initiatives, such as 608 and 610, did not make it on the ballot. With the assistance of public speaking engagements along with public events, and education, they successfully prohibited these initiatives.
The most extensive of the HOW, Whatcom County Coalition Council records are the subject files. Subjects cover a wide spectrum of gay and lesbian issues from HIV/AIDS and sexual orientation research to supportive religious statements and other like minded organizations. HOW also amassed a wide variety of materials pertaining to oppositional organizations. These materials consist of both local and national organizations from conservative groups like Focus on the Family, Lynden Youth Action Coalition, Colorado for Family Values and Paul Cameron to Newt Gingrich, Militias, and other hate groups. Formats in this series include articles, pamphlets, newspaper and magazine clippings, emails, press releases, activity fliers, and other printed material. Subject files were maintained in the order that HOW originally utilized them. They are coded in parentheses from 100 to 1000 and arranged by subject.
The reference files are mostly articles, organized by title. They contain many of the same themes contained within the subject files. Articles such as “Ideas for Handling Distress Patterns and Attacks” and “Dealing with Homophobia” are found in these files. Similar to the subject files, the reference files contain information from and about conservative oppositional organizations. Opposition materials, such as “Violence and the Far Right” and “The Right’s Agenda,” make up the majority of the reference files. Also included in these files are various reports, workshop information, and newspaper clippings about gay and lesbian issues.
There is also ephemera which contain banners, buttons and stickers relating to HOW and their public outreach campaign. The audio visual material contains video tapes and audio cassettes of programs pertaining to gay and lesbian issues.
The Hands Off Washington Whatcom County Coalition Council records are arranged in accordance with the following series
Series I: Administrative, 1989-1995
Series II: Newsletters, 1994-1996
Series III: Speaker and Workshop Information, 1988-1995
Series IV: Subject Files, 1989-1996
Series V: Reference Files, 1989-1996
Series VI: Audio/Visual Material, 1994-1996
Series VII: Ephemera, 1995
The collection is open to the public.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Hands Off Washington (Organization). Whatcom County Coalition Council; Washington Citizens for Fairness (Organization)
Gay rights -- Washington (State) -- History -- Sources.; Gays -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Washington (State) -- History -- Sources.; Lesbians -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Washington (State) -- History -- Sources.; Homosexuality -- Law and legislation -- Washington (State) -- History -- Sources.; Homosexuality -- Political aspects -- Washington (State) -- History -- Sources.; Gay liberation movement -- Washington (State) -- History -- Sources.; Legislation -- Washington (State) -- History -- Sources.; Gays -- Civil rights -- Washington (State) -- History -- Sources.; Gay rights -- Washington (State) -- Whatcom County -- Citizen participation -- History -- Sources.; Lesbians -- Civil rights -- Washington (State) -- History -- Sources.; Referendum -- Washington (State) -- History -- Sources.
Gays and Lesbians; Civil Rights; Civic Activism
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Administrative Records, 1989-1995; Series I
  - Hands Off Washington Office Log, 1995 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Meeting minutes, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Washington Citizens for Fairness/Hands Off Washington—Coalition Council, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Treasury Files (1), 1995 July -1995 December (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Treasury Files (2), 1995 January - 1995 June (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Public Relations, Press Secretary Notebook, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Washington Citizens for Fairness Affiliate, 1995 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - HOW Steering Committee, undated (Box-folder 1/8)
  - HOW Steering Committee—media monitoring, 1995 January (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Voter ID & Voter Targeting, undated (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Model Field Plan Outline, 1995 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - HOW/Washington Citizens for Fairness Information Request Forms, undated (Box-folder 1/12)
  - HOW Endorsement and Monthly Pledge Form, undated (Box-folder 1/13)
  - HOW Endorsement List, undated (Box-folder 1/14)
- Newsletters, 1994-1996; Series II
  - HOW Newsletters, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - HOW Newsletters, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - HOW Newsletters-other branches, 1995 (Box-folder 1/17)
- Speaker and Workshop Information, 1988-1995; Series III
  - Decline to Sign Workshop, 1995 June 10 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Master Copies for Speakers, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Speaker Bureau Lists and Questionnaires, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Speaker Bureau Resource Manual, undated (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Speaker Bureau Resource Manual, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Speaker Information and Model Field Plan Outline, undated (Box-folder 1/23)
  - Speaker Packet, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 1/24)
  - Speaker Packet, 1994 (Box-folder 1/25)
  - Speaker Training, 1994 (Box-folder 1/26)
  - Speaker Training packet, 1994 (Box-folder 1/27)
  - Training Packet (Seattle Office), 1994 (Box-folder 1/28)
  - Workshop Informational kit, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 1/29)
  - Workshop Informational kit, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 1/30)
- Subject Files, 1989-1996; Series IV
  The number in parentheses is the filing system that Hands Off Washington, Whatcom County Coalition Council used in the organization of their records.
  - HOW State Information (100), undated (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Masters HOW/Washington Citizens for Fairness Generated Forms and Graphics (200), undated (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Relevant Information Initiatives 166 &167 (201), 1995 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Resources (205), 1993 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Action Alert (207), 1993-1995 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - HOW Initiative (208), 1993-1995 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Initiative Process (210), 1995 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Letters to the Editor and Columns (211), 1993-1995 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Publicity Ideas (212), 1994 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - House Bill 1171 (214), undated (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Internet Lists (255), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Media Watch –Washington State (301), 1993-1995 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Rural Issues/Strategies (302), undated (Box-folder 2/13)
  - 1994 November Elections – Endorsements/Results (303) (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Political Cartoons (304), 1994 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Past Proposed Legislation (Old) Texts (306), 1994-1996 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - House Bill 1443 (305), 1994 (Box-folder 2/17)
  - Initiatives 608 & 610 – Clippings and Articles (307), 1994 (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Miscellaneous States (400), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2/19)
  - Colorado (404), 1995 (Box-folder 2/20)
  - Idaho (405), 1993-1995 (Box-folder 2/21)
  - Ohio (406), 1993-1995 (Box-folder 2/22)
  - Oregon (407), 1993-1995 (Box-folder 2/23)
  - Understanding The Religious Right: General (501), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2/24)
  - Understanding The Religious Right 2: General (501), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2/25)
  - Militias (500), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2/26)
  - Paul Cameron (540), 1994 (Box-folder 2/27)
  - Citizens Alliance of Washington (550), 1994 (Box-folder 2/28)
  - Colorado For Family Values (553), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2/29)
  - Focus on the Family Colorado (554), 1994 (Box-folder 2/30)
  - Gingrich, Newt (555), 1995 (Box-folder 2/31)
  - Equal Rights Not Special Rights; Initiative 608 & 166 (556), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2/32)
  - Youth Action Coalition Lynden – The Smalls (559), 1994 (Box-folder 2/33)
  - Lynden (561), 1994 (Box-folder 2/34)
  - Concerned Women for America (563), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2/35)
  - National Legislation (700), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2/36)
  - Affirmative Action (701), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2/37)
  - Educational Issues (703), 1995 (Box-folder 2/38)
  - Employment Non-discrimination Policy –Federal (705), 1993-1994 (Box-folder 2/39)
  - Job Discrimination (706), 1993-1995 (Box-folder 2/40)
  - National News Hate Crimes (707), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2/41)
  - Military (708), 1993-1995 (Box-folder 2/42)
  - Visual Media (709), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2/43)
  - Aids/HIV (801), 1991-1995 (Box-folder 2/44)
  - Civil Rights Constitutional Issues (802), 1993-1995 (Box-folder 2/45)
  - Countering Homophobia—Questionnaire Regarding Lesbians and Gays (802), undated (Box-folder 2/46)
  - Hate Crimes – Violence (804), 1993-1995 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Families (805), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Gay Income (806), 1994 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Marriage (807), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Symbols and Iconography (808), 1994 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Domestic Partner Benefits (809), 1991-1995 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Religious Statements – Supportive (811), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Gay Youth (812), 1993-1995 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Sexual Orientation Research (813), 1992-1996 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Heroes (815), 1993-1995 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Parents, Friends and Families of Lesbians and Gays (PFLAG) (900), 1995 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Human Rights Task Force Whatcom County (900), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Northwest Coalition Against Malicious Harassment (NWCAMH) (902), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Human Rights Campaign Fund (903), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Ex-Gays (904), 1994-1995 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Newsletter Ideas (1000), 1994 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - International News (1100), 1994 (Box-folder 3/17)
- Reference Files, 1989-1996; Series V
  - “51 Leadership Principles to Remember” article, undated (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Action Kit: Fight the Right, undated (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Acts, Bills, Initiatives, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 3/20)
  - The Advocate July, October, and November, 1992 (Box-folder 3/21)
  - “Anti-Gay/Lesbian Violence Fact Sheet”, 1993 February (Box-folder 3/22)
  - Bigot Busters, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 3/23)
  - “Breaking Isolation” article, undated (Box-folder 3/24)
  - Cameron, Paul, undated (Box-folder 3/25)
  - Child Abuse Statistics, undated (Box-folder 3/26)
  - Citizens Alliance of Washington (CAW) information sheet, undated (Box-folder 3/27)
  - Citizens Alliance of Washington (CAW) Statement of Principles, undated (Box-folder 3/28)
  - “Civil Rights, Special Rights and Our Rights” article, undated (Box-folder 3/29)
  - Coalition for a Livable Washington, 1994 (Box-folder 3/30)
  - Concerns shared by both sides, 1992 (Box-folder 3/31)
  - “The Congregation for the Doctrine of Faith and Homosexuals: Rewriting the Moral Tradition” article, 1992 September 12 (Box-folder 3/32)
  - “The Covert Crusade” article, undated (Box-folder 3/33)
  - “Dealing with Homophobia” information sheet, undated (Box-folder 3/34)
  - Dignity Report 3 no. 1 and 2, 1995 (Box-folder 3/35)
  - “Divisions that Kill” article, undated (Box-folder 3/36)
  - Fight the Right: March on WA Edition; Oregon Speak Out Project, undated (Box-folder 3/37)
  - General State Legislative Information, 1994 (Box-folder 3/38)
  - General Newspaper Clippings, 1993-1996 (Box-folder 3/39)
  - Hands Against Hate fliers, undated (Box-folder 3/40)
  - “How the Right Stirs Black Homophobia” article, 1993 (Box-folder 3/41)
  - Humor and Reassurance, 1995 (Box-folder 3/42)
  - “Ideas for Handling Distress Patterns and Attacks” article, undated (Box-folder 3/43)
  - Information kit Opposition and Organization (1 of 2), 1989-1992 (Box-folder 3/44)
  - Information kit Opposition and Organization (2 of 2), 1989-1992 (Box-folder 3/45)
  - Initiative 166 & 167; 608, 1995 (Box-folder 3/46)
  - “Lesbian and Gay Families Issues Fact Sheet”, 1993 February (Box-folder 3/47)
  - Local Newspaper Clippings, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 3/48)
  - Local Opposition Information, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 3/49)
  - The New Republic: Straight America/Gay America, 1993 May 10 (Box-folder 3/50)
  - “The New Right” article, undated (Box-folder 3/51)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1995 (Box-folder 3/52)
  - Northwest Coalition Against Malicious Harassment (NWCAMH), Manual “Organizing Against Bigotry”, 1995 (Box-folder 3/53)
  - Northwest Coalition Against Malicious Harassment (NWCAMH), Newsletter “Northwest Beacon”, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 3/54)
  - Northwest Imperative, 1994 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Opposition Watch, 1994 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Peace Work: Violence, Nonviolence, and the 20th Century #232, 1993 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - “The Price of Democracy,” undated Public Education/Commodity Organization", 1992 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Public Education/Community Organization, 1992 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Raising Hell: A Citizen’s Guide to the Fine Art of Investigation, undated (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Reading List: Homosexuality and Christianity Positive Views, undated (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Re-evaluation Council, undated (Box-folder 4/8)
  - “Report of the Secretary’s Task Force on Youth Suicide,”, 1989 January (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Resource Notebook I, 1989-1994 (Box-folder 4/10)
  - Resource Notebook III, 1994 (Box-folder 4/11)
  - “The Right’s Agenda” article, 1994 (Box-folder 4/12)
  - Side by Side, 1993 (Box-folder 4/13)
  - “Spotlight on the Liberty Lobby” Covert Action 50, undated (Box-folder 4/14)
  - Stealth Campaign article, undated (Box-folder 4/15)
  - “Summary of Discussion Points Traditional Values Coalition Videotape ‘Gay Rights/Special Rights,” Fall 1993 and “Lesbian Baiting and Gay Baiting: How Homophobia is a Tool of Sexism,” undated, 1993 and undated (Box-folder 4/16)
  - Supportive Denominational Statements, undated (Box-folder 4/17)
  - “Violence and the Far Right” article, undated (Box-folder 4/18)
  - Washington Association of Sheriffs and Police Chiefs, 1993 January – June (Box-folder 4/19)
  - The Gay and Lesbian Address Book, 1995 (Box-folder 4/20)
- Audio/Visual Material, 1994-1996; Series VI
  - Video Cassettes, 1996; Subseries 1
    - Gay Agenda, 1996 May 15 (Box-folder 4/21)
    - In the Life, undated (Box-folder 4/22)
    - Straight from the heart, undated (Box-folder 4/23)
  - Audio Cassettes, 1994-1996; Subseries 2
    - Bonnie Lou and Robert Hawkins; Domestic Partnership on Campus, 1995 June 5; 1994 November 11 (Box-folder 4/24)
- Ephemera Material, 1995; Series VII
  - Posters, Pamphlets, Buttons and Banner, undated (Box-folder 4/25)
  - Bumper Stickers, undated (Box-folder 4/26)
  - HOW Activity Fliers, 1995 (Box-folder 4/27)